,Year,Month,Day,Content,Wikipedia,Summary,filteredRefs,num_refs,Ents,Ents_types
0,1965,January,30,State Funeral of Winston Churchill at St Paul's Cathedral in London. Then world's largest ever state funeral.,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Death_and_state_funeral_of_Winston_Churchill,"Sir Winston Churchill died on 24 January 1965, aged 90. His was the first state funeral for a non-royal family member since Lord Carson in 1935, and as of 2020 it remains the most recent state funeral in the United Kingdom. The official funeral lasted for four days. Planning for the funeral, known as Operation Hope Not, began 12 years before Churchill's death. It was initiated after Churchill's stroke in 1953 while in his second term as the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom. After several revisions due to Churchill's continued survival, the plan was issued on 26 January 1965, two days after his death. 
By decree of Queen Elizabeth II, his body lay in state at Westminster Hall for three days from 26 January. On 30 January, the order of funeral was held at St Paul's Cathedral. From there the body was transported by water along the River Thames to Waterloo station, accompanied by military salutations. In the afternoon he was buried at St Martin's Churchyard at Bladon, the resting place of his ancestors and his brother. Attended by representatives from 120 countries, 6,000 people, and unusually by the Queen, more than 1,000 police and security personnel, involving nine military bands, 18 military battalions, 16 Royal Air Force English Electric Lightning fighter jets, a special boat MV Havengore and a train hauled by Winston Churchill, homage paid by 321,360 people, and witnessed by over 350 million people, it was the largest state funeral in history.

","{2051, 7, 2568, 28, 4642, 4138, 1583, 4661, 576, 2112, 580, 2119, 75, 1616, 2647, 3676, 2141, 1633, 1646, 1136, 3705, 2171, 127, 3199, 1153, 1162, 3722, 1678, 2191, 1170, 661, 663, 1177, 1192, 3243, 1709, 3252, 703, 4287, 1730, 1732, 3272, 2767, 4307, 3803, 1757, 1251, 3812, 3813, 2278, 2793, 234, 1260, 3322, 1275, 3842, 4871, 1288, 4879, 2322, 3862, 3874, 3365, 4407, 4923, 843, 2891, 4940, 4430, 2388, 2901, 3413, 3927, 1888, 1890, 4971, 2415, 3954, 889, 3451, 892, 387, 2955, 3979, 1424, 3989, 418, 4516, 4526, 2483, 2487, 952, 1465, 3524, 453, 1491, 468, 4051, 990, 1508, 2026, 1526, 2039, 3578, 4605}",105,"[""St Paul's"", 'London', 'Winston Churchill', '24 January 1965', '90', 'Carson', '1935', '2020', 'the United Kingdom', 'four days', '12 years', 'Churchill', 'Churchill', '1953', 'the United Kingdom', 'Churchill', '26 January 1965', 'two days', 'Queen Elizabeth II', 'Westminster Hall', 'three days', '26 January', '30 January', ""St Paul's"", 'the River Thames', 'Waterloo', ""St Martin's"", 'Churchyard at Bladon', 'Queen', 'Royal Air Force', 'English', 'Winston Churchill']","['FAC', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'FAC', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'FAC', 'LOC', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'LANGUAGE', 'PERSON']"
1,1965,March,18,"Cosmonaut Alexey Leonov, leaving his spacecraft Voskhod 2 for 12 minutes, becomes the first person to walk in space",,,"{2210, 4235, 4971, 467, 2004, 4307, 1979, 4413}",8,"['Cosmonaut Alexey Leonov', 'Voskhod 2']","['ORG', 'PERSON']"
2,1965,March,22,US confirms its troops used chemical warfare against the Vietcong,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/People%27s_Army_of_Vietnam,"The People's Army of Vietnam (PAVN; Vietnamese: Quân đội Nhân dân Việt Nam), also known as the Vietnamese People's Army (VPA), is the military force of the Socialist Republic of Vietnam. The PAVN is a part of the Vietnam People's Armed Forces and includes: Ground Force (including Strategic Rear Forces), Navy, Air Force, Border Defence Force, and Coast Guard. However, Vietnam does not have a separate Ground Force or Army branch. All ground troops, army corps, military districts and specialised arms belong to the Ministry of Defence, directly under the command of the Central Military Commission, the Minister of Defence, and the General Staff of the Vietnam People's Army. The military flag of the PAVN is the flag of the Socialist Republic of Vietnam, with the words Quyết thắng (Determination to win) added in yellow at the top left.
During the French Indochina War (1946–1954), the PAVN was often referred to as the Việt Minh. In the context of the Vietnam War (1955–1975), the army was referred to as the North Vietnamese Army (NVA). This allowed writers, the U.S. military, and the general public, to distinguish northern communists from the southern communists, called Viet Cong or National Liberation Front. However, both groups ultimately worked under the same command structure. The Viet Cong was considered a branch of the VPA by the North Vietnamese. In 2010 the PAVN undertook the role of leading the 1,000th Anniversary Parade in Hanoi by performing their biggest parade in history.","{1026, 2568, 521, 524, 528, 4113, 1562, 28, 2589, 2590, 2078, 1058, 39, 551, 1576, 2601, 1584, 2104, 1081, 66, 3139, 2628, 1616, 4688, 1622, 2649, 3163, 4192, 2152, 619, 2155, 3692, 1649, 629, 2169, 3195, 640, 2176, 2703, 144, 3727, 4768, 2213, 174, 4785, 1204, 3777, 1228, 2764, 4307, 3285, 3804, 3805, 4829, 3808, 3303, 4330, 1783, 1275, 1292, 1808, 3869, 4895, 3874, 294, 4905, 4916, 311, 2875, 3903, 1857, 4941, 4942, 1370, 3427, 1386, 4472, 890, 3451, 4993, 4994, 2955, 3979, 1432, 2475, 4020, 4024, 5059, 452, 4549, 2507, 2508, 1997, 5067, 5079, 3034, 1502, 3040, 4074, 492, 5107, 2040, 1017, 3578, 4605}",105,"['US', 'Vietcong', ""The People's Army"", 'Vietnam', 'PAVN', 'Vietnamese', 'Nhân', 'Việt Nam', ""the Vietnamese People's Army"", 'VPA', 'the Socialist Republic of Vietnam', 'PAVN', ""the Vietnam People's Armed Forces"", 'Ground Force', 'Strategic Rear Forces', 'Navy', 'Air Force', 'Border Defence Force', 'Coast Guard', 'Vietnam', 'Ground Force', 'Army', 'army corps', 'the Ministry of Defence', 'the Central Military Commission', 'the General Staff of', ""the Vietnam People's Army"", 'PAVN', 'the Socialist Republic of Vietnam', 'Quyết', 'the French Indochina War', 'PAVN', 'the Việt Minh', 'the Vietnam War', 'the North Vietnamese Army', 'NVA', 'U.S.', 'Viet Cong', 'National Liberation Front', 'The Viet Cong', 'VPA', 'the North Vietnamese', '2010', 'PAVN', 'Hanoi']","['GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'EVENT', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'EVENT', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'EVENT', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'EVENT', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'GPE']"
3,1965,May,5,First large-scale US Army ground units arrive in South Vietnam,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Military_history_of_Australia_during_the_Vietnam_War,"Australia's involvement in the Vietnam War began with a small commitment of 30 military advisors in 1962, and increased over the following decade to a peak of 7,672 Australian personnel following the Menzies Government's April 1965 decision to upgrade its military commitment to South Vietnam's security. By the time the last Australian personnel were withdrawn in 1972, the Vietnam War had become Australia's longest war, and was only recently surpassed by Australia's long term commitment of combat forces to the War in Afghanistan. It remains Australia's largest force contribution to a foreign conflict since the Second World War and was also the most controversial in Australian society since the conscription controversy during the First World War. Although initially enjoying broad support due to concerns about the spread of communism in Southeast Asia, a vocal anti-war movement developed in response to Australia's programme of conscription.
The withdrawal of Australia's forces from South Vietnam began in November 1970, under the Gorton Government, when 8 RAR completed its tour of duty and was not replaced. A phased withdrawal followed, and by 11 January 1973 Australian involvement in hostilities in Vietnam had ceased. Nevertheless, Australian troops from the Australian Embassy Platoon remained deployed in the country until 1 July 1973, and Australian forces were deployed briefly in April 1975, during the Fall of Saigon, to evacuate personnel from the Australian embassy. Approximately 60,000 Australians served in the war; 521 were killed and more than 3,000 were wounded.

","{640, 4993, 3586, 4994, 3332, 4871, 1289, 2703, 3727, 3989, 3734, 4895, 4768, 2721, 1058, 4899, 2342, 4775, 4905, 3882, 4268, 815, 1584, 4400, 563, 2483, 2104, 1979, 3648, 3777, 452, 964, 1095, 4807, 75, 4300, 717, 4942, 5067, 4307, 2388, 5077, 1622, 3927, 3034, 4192, 4704, 2152, 4971, 1649, 5107, 632, 4986, 3195}",54,"['US Army', 'South Vietnam', 'Australia', 'the Vietnam War', '1962', 'the following decade', 'Australian', ""the Menzies Government's"", 'April 1965', ""South Vietnam's"", 'Australian', '1972', 'the Vietnam War', 'Australia', 'Australia', 'Afghanistan', 'Australia', 'the Second World War', 'Australian', 'the First World War', 'Southeast Asia', 'Australia', 'Australia', 'South Vietnam', 'November 1970', 'the Gorton Government', 'RAR', '11 January 1973', 'Australian', 'Vietnam', 'Australian', 'Australian', 'Embassy Platoon', '1 July 1973', 'Australian', 'April 1975', 'the Fall of Saigon', 'Australian', 'Australians']","['ORG', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'EVENT', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'EVENT', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'EVENT', 'NORP', 'EVENT', 'LOC', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'NORP']"
4,1965,June,7,"The Supreme Court of the United States decides on Griswold v. Connecticut, effectively legalizing the use of contraception by married couples",https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roe_v._Wade,"Roe v. Wade, 410 U.S. 113 (1973), was a landmark decision of the U.S. Supreme Court in which the Court ruled that the Constitution of the United States protects a pregnant woman's liberty to choose to have an abortion without excessive government restriction. It struck down many U.S. state and federal abortion laws, and prompted an ongoing national debate in the United States about whether and to what extent abortion should be legal, who should decide the legality of abortion, what methods the Supreme Court should use in constitutional adjudication, and what the role  of religious and moral views in the political sphere should be. Roe v. Wade reshaped U.S. politics, dividing much of the United States into abortion rights and anti-abortion movements, while activating grassroots movements on both sides.
The decision involved the case of a woman named Norma McCorvey—known in her lawsuit under the pseudonym ""Jane Roe""—who in 1969 became pregnant with her third child and wanted an abortion. However, McCorvey lived in Texas, where abortion was illegal except when necessary to save the mother's life. She was referred to lawyers Sarah Weddington and Linda Coffee, who filed a lawsuit on her behalf in U.S. federal court against her local district attorney, Henry Wade, alleging that Texas's abortion laws were unconstitutional. A three-judge panel of the U.S. District Court for the Northern District of Texas heard the case and ruled in her favor. Texas then appealed this ruling directly to the U.S. Supreme Court, which agreed to hear the case.
In January 1973, the Supreme Court issued a 7–2 decision holding that the Due Process Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution provides a ""right to privacy"" that protects a pregnant woman's right to choose whether or not to have an abortion. However, it held that this right is not absolute, and must be balanced against the government's interests in protecting women's health and protecting prenatal life. The Court resolved this balancing test by tying state regulation of abortion to the three trimesters of pregnancy: during the first trimester, governments could not prohibit abortions at all; during the second trimester, governments could require reasonable health regulations; during the third trimester, abortions could be prohibited entirely so long as the laws contained exceptions for cases when they were necessary to save the life or health of the mother. The Court classified the right to choose to have an abortion as ""fundamental"", which required courts to evaluate challenged abortion laws under the ""strict scrutiny"" standard, the highest level of judicial review in the United States.Roe was criticized by some in the legal community, and some have called the decision a form of judicial activism. In a prominent Yale Law Journal article published soon after the decision was issued, the legal scholar John Hart Ely criticized Roe as a decision that ""is not constitutional law and gives almost no sense of an obligation to try to be."" In 1992, the Supreme Court revisited and modified its legal rulings in Roe in the case of Planned Parenthood v. Casey. In Casey, the Court reaffirmed Roe's holding that a woman's right to choose to have an abortion is constitutionally protected, but abandoned Roe's trimester framework in favor of a standard based on fetal viability, and overruled Roe's requirement that government regulations on abortion be subjected to the strict scrutiny standard.","{640, 4993, 3842, 4994, 4101, 7, 2955, 2703, 1168, 3727, 3989, 4895, 4768, 2169, 290, 2210, 2982, 4134, 1576, 2601, 4905, 2171, 815, 1201, 2740, 309, 4024, 2875, 4539, 452, 4549, 1222, 967, 2122, 971, 2507, 2509, 4682, 4815, 3322, 595, 2388, 3795, 1622, 4307, 5077, 3805, 3180, 4589, 1649, 889, 4474, 3451, 4605}",54,"['The Supreme Court', 'the United States', 'Griswold', 'Connecticut', 'Roe v. Wade', 'U.S.', '1973', 'the U.S. Supreme Court', 'Court', 'the Constitution of the United States', 'U.S.', 'the United States', 'the Supreme Court', 'Roe v. Wade', 'U.S.', 'the United States', 'Norma McCorvey', 'Jane', '1969', 'McCorvey', 'Texas', 'Sarah Weddington', 'Linda Coffee', 'U.S.', 'Henry Wade', 'Texas', 'the U.S. District Court', 'the Northern District', 'Texas', 'Texas', 'the U.S. Supreme Court', 'January 1973', 'the Supreme Court', 'the Due Process Clause', 'the Fourteenth Amendment', 'the U.S. Constitution', 'Court', 'Court', 'the United States', 'Roe', 'Yale Law Journal', 'John Hart Ely', 'Roe', '1992', 'the Supreme Court', 'Roe', 'Planned Parenthood', 'Casey', 'Casey', 'Court', 'Roe', 'Roe', 'Roe']","['ORG', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'LAW', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'LAW', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'LAW', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'LOC', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'LAW', 'LAW', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'LAW', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'LAW', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'LAW', 'LAW', 'LAW']"
5,1965,August,6,US President Lyndon B. Johnson signs the Voting Rights Act prohibiting voting discrimination against minorities,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voting_Rights_Act_of_1965,"The Voting Rights Act of 1965 is a landmark piece of federal legislation in the United States that prohibits racial discrimination in voting. It was signed into law by United States President Lyndon B. Johnson during the height of the civil rights movement on August 6, 1965, and Congress later amended the Act five times to expand its protections. Designed to enforce the voting rights guaranteed by the Fourteenth and Fifteenth Amendments to the United States Constitution, the Act secured the right to vote for racial minorities throughout the country, especially in the South. According to the U.S. Department of Justice, the Act is considered to be the most effective piece of federal civil rights legislation ever enacted in the country.The Act contains numerous provisions that regulate elections. The Act's ""general provisions"" provide nationwide protections for voting rights. Section 2 is a general provision that prohibits every state and local government from imposing any voting law that results in discrimination against racial or language minorities. Other general provisions specifically outlaw literacy tests and similar devices that were historically used to disenfranchise racial minorities.
The Act also contains ""special provisions"" that apply to only certain jurisdictions. A core special provision is the Section 5 preclearance requirement, which prohibits certain jurisdictions from implementing any change affecting voting without receiving preapproval from the U.S. Attorney General or the U.S. District Court for D.C. that the change does not discriminate against protected minorities. Another special provision requires jurisdictions containing significant language minority populations to provide bilingual ballots and other election materials.
Section 5 and most other special provisions apply to jurisdictions encompassed by the ""coverage formula"" prescribed in Section 4(b). The coverage formula was originally designed to encompass jurisdictions that engaged in egregious voting discrimination in 1965, and Congress updated the formula in 1970 and 1975. In Shelby County v. Holder (2013), the U.S. Supreme Court struck down the coverage formula as unconstitutional, reasoning that it was no longer responsive to current conditions. The Court did not strike down Section 5, but without a coverage formula, Section 5 is unenforceable.","{1378, 4741}",2,"['US', 'Lyndon B. Johnson', 'the Voting Rights Act', 'The Voting Rights Act', '1965', 'the United States', 'United States', 'Lyndon B. Johnson', 'August 6, 1965', 'Congress', 'Act five', 'Fifteenth Amendments', 'the United States Constitution', 'Act', 'South', 'the U.S. Department of Justice', 'Act', 'Act', 'Act', 'Section 2', 'Act', 'Section 5', 'U.S.', 'U.S.', 'District Court', 'D.C.', 'Section 5', 'Section 4(b', '1965', 'Congress', '1970', '1975', 'Shelby County', '2013', 'the U.S. Supreme Court', 'Court', 'Section 5', 'Section 5']","['GPE', 'PERSON', 'LAW', 'LAW', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'LAW', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'LAW', 'LOC', 'ORG', 'LAW', 'LAW', 'LAW', 'LAW', 'LAW', 'LAW', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'LAW', 'LAW', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'LAW', 'LAW']"
6,1965,August,9,Singapore separates from the Federation of Malaysia and gains its independence,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Singapore_in_Malaysia,"Singapore was one of the 14 states of Malaysia from 1963 to 1965. Malaysia was formed on 16 September 1963 by the merger of the Federation of Malaya with the former British colonies of North Borneo, Sarawak and Singapore. This marked the end of a 144-year British rule in Singapore which began with the founding of modern Singapore by Sir Stamford Raffles in 1819.
The union was unstable due to distrust and ideological differences between leaders of Singapore and of the federal government of Malaysia. They often disagreed about finance, politics and racial policies. Singapore continued to face significant trade restrictions despite promises of a common market in return for a large proportion of her tax revenues, and retaliated by withholding loans to Sabah and Sarawak. In the political arena, the Malay-based United Malays National Organisation (UMNO) and Singapore-based People's Action Party (PAP), entered each other's political arenas, despite previous agreements not to do so. These resulted in major race riots in Singapore in 1964, which were attributed (at least in part) to instigation by UMNO and its Malay-language newspaper Utusan Melayu for affirmative action for Malays in Singapore.These culminated in the decision by Malaysian Prime Minister Tunku Abdul Rahman to expel Singapore from the Federation, and on 9 August 1965, Singapore became the first and only modern country to date to gain independence unwillingly. While their paths have diverged subsequently, both countries continue to co-operate in many areas and organisations such as ASEAN and the Five Power Defence Arrangements.","{128, 4993, 3842, 640, 901, 7, 3989, 4891, 4768, 2210, 4134, 2171, 2096, 561, 4539, 4549, 967, 2122, 971, 2507, 4682, 4815, 595, 467, 3795, 4307, 5077, 3834, 3803, 2398, 1502, 2529, 3434, 4971, 3180, 4589, 3702, 889, 4474, 3451, 5117}",41,"['Singapore', 'the Federation of Malaysia', 'Singapore', 'Malaysia', '1963 to', '1965', 'Malaysia', '16 September 1963', 'the Federation of Malaya', 'British', 'North Borneo', 'Sarawak', 'Singapore', 'British', 'Singapore', 'Singapore', 'Stamford Raffles', '1819', 'Singapore', 'Malaysia', 'Singapore', 'Sabah', 'Sarawak', 'Malay', 'United Malays National Organisation', 'Singapore', ""People's Action Party"", 'Singapore', '1964', 'UMNO', 'Malay', 'Utusan Melayu', 'Malays', 'Singapore', 'Malaysian', 'Tunku Abdul Rahman', 'Singapore', '9 August 1965', 'Singapore', 'ASEAN', 'the Five Power Defence Arrangements']","['GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'LANGUAGE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'PRODUCT', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'ORG']"
7,1965,September,22,"India and Pakistan cease-fire goes into effect, ending the Indo-Pakistani War",https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indo-Pakistani_War_of_1965,"The Indo-Pakistani War of 1965 was a culmination of skirmishes that took place between April 1965 and September 1965 between Pakistan and India. The conflict began following Pakistan's Operation Gibraltar, which was designed to infiltrate forces into Jammu and Kashmir to precipitate an insurgency against Indian rule. India retaliated by launching a full-scale military attack on West Pakistan. The seventeen-day war caused thousands of casualties on both sides and witnessed the largest engagement of armored vehicles and the largest tank battle since World War II. Hostilities between the two countries ended after a United Nations-mandated ceasefire was declared following diplomatic intervention by the Soviet Union and the United States, and the subsequent issuance of the Tashkent Declaration. Much of the war was fought by the countries' land forces in Kashmir and along the border between India and Pakistan. This war saw the largest amassing of troops in Kashmir since the Partition of India in 1947, a number that was overshadowed only during the 2001–2002 military standoff between India and Pakistan. Most of the battles were fought by opposing infantry and armoured units, with substantial backing from air forces, and naval operations. Many details of this war, like those of other Indo-Pakistani Wars, remain unclear.India had the upper hand over Pakistan when the ceasefire was declared.  Although the two countries fought to a standoff, the conflict is seen as a strategic and political defeat for Pakistan, as it had neither succeeded in fomenting insurrection in Kashmir nor had it been able to gain meaningful support at an international level.Internationally, the war was viewed in the context of the greater Cold War, and resulted in a significant geopolitical shift in the subcontinent. Before the war, the United States and the United Kingdom had been major material allies of both India and Pakistan, as their primary suppliers of military hardware and foreign developmental aid. During and after the conflict, both India and Pakistan felt betrayed by the perceived lack of support by the western powers for their respective positions; those feelings of betrayal were increased with the imposition of an American and British embargo on military aid to the opposing sides. As a consequence, India and Pakistan openly developed closer relationships with the Soviet Union and China, respectively. The perceived negative stance of the western powers during the conflict, and during the 1971 war, has continued to affect relations between the West and the subcontinent. In spite of improved relations with the U.S. and Britain since the end of the Cold War, the conflict generated a deep distrust of both countries within the subcontinent which to an extent lingers to this day.",set(),0,"['India', 'Pakistan', 'the Indo-Pakistani War', 'The Indo-Pakistani War', '1965', 'April 1965', 'September 1965', 'Pakistan', 'India', 'Pakistan', 'Operation Gibraltar', 'Jammu', 'Kashmir', 'Indian', 'India', 'West Pakistan', 'seventeen-day', 'World War II', 'United Nations', 'the Soviet Union', 'the United States', 'the Tashkent Declaration', 'Kashmir', 'India', 'Pakistan', 'Kashmir', 'the Partition of India', '1947', 'India', 'Pakistan', 'Indo', 'India', 'Pakistan', 'Pakistan', 'Kashmir', 'Cold War', 'the United States', 'the United Kingdom', 'India', 'Pakistan', 'India', 'Pakistan', 'American', 'British', 'India', 'Pakistan', 'the Soviet Union', 'China', 'the 1971 war', 'West', 'U.S.', 'Britain', 'the end of', 'the Cold War', 'this day']","['GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'LOC', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'LOC', 'DATE', 'EVENT', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'LAW', 'LOC', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'LOC', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'LOC', 'EVENT', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'EVENT', 'LOC', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'EVENT', 'DATE']"
8,1965,December,7,Pope Paul VI & Orthodox Patriarch Athenagoras I simultaneously lift mutual excommunications that led to split of 2 churches in 1054,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_Christianity,"The history of Christianity concerns the Christian religion, Christendom, and the Church with its various denominations, from the 1st century to the present.
Christianity originated with the ministry of Jesus in the 1st century Roman province of Judea. According to the Gospels, Jesus was a Jewish teacher and healer who proclaimed the imminent Kingdom of God, and was crucified c.30‑33 AD. His followers believed that he was then raised from the dead and exalted by God, and would return soon at the inception of God's Kingdom.
The earliest followers of Jesus were apocalyptic Jewish Christians. Due to the inclusion of gentiles, the developing early Christian Church gradually grew apart from Judaism and Jewish Christianity during the first two centuries of the Christian Era.
In 313, Emperor Constantine I issued the Edict of Milan legalizing Christian worship. In 380, with the Edict of Thessalonica put forth under Theodosius I, the Roman Empire officially adopted Trinitarian Christianity as its state religion, and Christianity established itself as a predominantly gentile religion in the state church of the Roman Empire.
Christological debates about the human and divine nature of Jesus consumed the Christian Church for a couple of centuries, and seven eucumenical councils were called to resolve these debates. Arianism was condemned at the First Council of Nicea (325), which supported the Trinitarian doctrine as expounded in the Nicene Creed.
In the early Middle Ages, missionary activities spread Christianity towards the west among German peoples. During the High Middle Ages, eastern and western Christianity grew apart, leading to the East-West Schism of 1054. Growing criticism of the Roman Catholic ecclesiological structure and its behaviour, led to the Protestant movement of the 16th century and the split of western Christianity.
Since the Renaissance era, with western colonialism, Christianity has expanded throughout the world. Today there are more than two billion Christians worldwide, and Christianity has become the world's largest religion. Within the last century, as the influence of Christianity has waned in the West, it has also rapidly grown in the East and the Global South in China, South Korea and much of sub-Saharan Africa. There has been recent growth of Christianity in Iran.","{1031, 521, 1038, 1041, 2579, 28, 1058, 1584, 2615, 2104, 4154, 576, 3139, 580, 70, 2119, 3656, 2131, 1109, 1622, 2647, 3676, 4192, 2150, 2152, 3692, 2191, 1178, 2721, 4774, 1192, 1193, 176, 4785, 703, 3777, 1240, 4829, 1251, 3299, 1783, 1272, 3322, 1275, 767, 3842, 1795, 3332, 4868, 4871, 283, 4895, 1824, 1830, 3886, 2874, 3903, 1346, 2372, 843, 2382, 2898, 2901, 1370, 3437, 885, 1397, 890, 4993, 4994, 900, 2955, 1452, 4017, 2487, 3005, 1471, 452, 964, 1997, 1491, 3553, 2026, 4074, 3054, 498, 1015, 1017, 3578, 4605}",90,"['Pope Paul VI & Orthodox', 'Patriarch Athenagoras', '1054', 'Christianity', 'Christian', 'Christendom', 'Church', 'the 1st century', 'Christianity', 'the ministry of Jesus', 'the 1st century', 'Roman province', 'Judea', 'Gospels', 'Jesus', 'Jewish', 'God', 'Jesus', 'Jewish', 'Christians', 'Judaism', 'Jewish', 'the first two centuries', 'the Christian Era', 'Milan', 'Christian', 'the Edict of Thessalonica', 'Theodosius I', 'the Roman Empire', 'Trinitarian Christianity', 'Christianity', 'the Roman Empire', 'Jesus', 'the Christian Church', 'a couple of centuries', 'the First Council of Nicea', 'Trinitarian', 'the Nicene Creed', 'the early Middle Ages', 'Christianity', 'German', 'the High Middle Ages', 'eastern', 'Christianity', 'the East-West Schism', '1054', 'Roman Catholic', 'Protestant', 'the 16th century', 'Christianity', 'Renaissance', 'Christianity', 'Today', 'Christians', 'Christianity', 'the last century', 'Christianity', 'East', 'the Global South', 'China', 'South Korea', 'Saharan Africa', 'Christianity', 'Iran']","['ORG', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'LOC', 'PRODUCT', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'LOC', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'LOC', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'LOC', 'LOC', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE']"
9,1965,December,8,Pope Paul VI signs 2nd Vatican council,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pope_John_Paul_II,"Pope John Paul II (Latin: Ioannes Paulus II; Italian: Giovanni Paolo II; Polish: Jan Paweł II; born Karol Józef Wojtyła [ˈkarɔl ˈjuzɛv vɔjˈtɨwa]; 18 May 1920 – 2 April 2005) was head of the Catholic Church and sovereign of the Vatican City State from 1978 to 2005. 
He was elected pope by the second papal conclave of 1978, which was called after Pope John Paul I, who had been elected in August to succeed Pope Paul VI, died after 33 days. Cardinal Wojtyła was elected on the third day of the conclave and adopted the name of his predecessor in tribute to him. John Paul II is recognised as helping to end Communist rule in his native Poland and eventually all of Europe. John Paul II significantly improved the Catholic Church's relations with Judaism, Islam, and the Eastern Orthodox Church. He upheld the Church's teachings on such matters as the right to life, artificial contraception, the ordination of women, and a celibate clergy, and although he supported the reforms of the Second Vatican Council, he was seen as generally conservative in their interpretation.He was one of the most travelled world leaders in history, visiting 129 countries during his pontificate. As part of his special emphasis on the universal call to holiness, he beatified 1,340 and canonised 483 people, more than the combined tally of his predecessors during the preceding five centuries. By the time of his death, he had named most of the College of Cardinals, consecrated or co-consecrated a large number of the world's bishops, and ordained many priests.John Paul II was the second longest-serving pope in modern history after Pope Pius IX. Born in Poland, John Paul II was the first non-Italian pope since the 16th-century Pope Adrian VI. John Paul II's cause for canonisation commenced one month after his death with the traditional five-year waiting period waived. On 19 December 2009, John Paul II was proclaimed venerable by his successor, Benedict XVI, and was beatified on 1 May 2011 (Divine Mercy Sunday) after the Congregation for the Causes of Saints attributed one miracle to his intercession, the healing of a French nun from Parkinson's disease. A second miracle was approved on 2 July 2013, and confirmed by Pope Francis two days later. John Paul II was canonised on 27 April 2014 (again Divine Mercy Sunday), together with Pope John XXIII. On 11 September 2014, Pope Francis added these two optional memorials to the worldwide General Roman Calendar of saints. It is traditional to celebrate saints' feast days on the anniversary of their deaths, but that of John Paul II (22 October) is celebrated on the anniversary of his papal inauguration. Posthumously, he has been referred to by some Catholics as ""St. John Paul the Great"", although the title has no official recognition.","{640, 4993, 3842, 2051, 900, 4994, 7, 903, 1162, 2955, 1036, 3979, 2703, 144, 1168, 1275, 4756, 3989, 1177, 28, 4895, 4768, 1058, 3874, 4775, 1192, 1576, 1323, 2475, 174, 1583, 1584, 4526, 2483, 4020, 4661, 2104, 4024, 4536, 3903, 576, 4671, 452, 1732, 3524, 3272, 843, 208, 2004, 2388, 1622, 2647, 2901, 2529, 3427, 2278, 3046, 234, 3693, 494, 4589, 1649, 2040, 2169, 3322, 3451, 4605, 4986}",68,"['Pope Paul VI', 'Vatican', 'John Paul II', 'Latin', 'Italian', 'Giovanni Paolo II', 'Polish', 'Jan Paweł II', 'Karol Józef Wojtyła', 'May 1920', '2 April 2005', 'the Catholic Church', 'the Vatican City State', '1978 to 2005', '1978', 'John Paul', 'August', 'Paul VI', '33 days', 'Cardinal Wojtyła', 'the third day', 'John Paul II', 'Communist', 'Poland', 'Europe', 'John Paul II', ""the Catholic Church's"", 'Islam', 'the Eastern Orthodox Church', 'Church', 'the Second Vatican Council', 'the preceding five centuries', 'the College of Cardinals', 'John Paul II', 'Pope Pius IX', 'Poland', 'John Paul II', 'non-Italian', 'the 16th-century', ""John Paul II's"", 'one month', 'five-year', '19 December 2009', 'John Paul II', 'Benedict XVI', '1 May 2011', 'Sunday', 'Saints', 'French', '2 July 2013', 'Pope Francis', 'two days later', 'John Paul II', '27 April 2014', 'Divine Mercy', 'Sunday', 'John XXIII', '11 September 2014', 'Pope Francis', 'Roman Calendar', 'John Paul II', '22 October', 'Catholics']","['PERSON', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'FAC', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'LOC', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'NORP']"
10,1965,March,2,"One of the most popular musical films of all time, ""The Sound of Music"", starring Julie Andrews and Christopher Plummer, is released (Academy Awards Best Picture 1966)",https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sound_of_Music_(film),"The Sound of Music is a 1965 American musical drama film produced and directed by Robert Wise, and starring Julie Andrews and Christopher Plummer, with Richard Haydn and Eleanor Parker. The film is an adaptation of the 1959 stage musical of the same name, composed by Richard Rodgers with lyrics by Oscar Hammerstein II. The film's screenplay was written by Ernest Lehman, adapted from the stage musical's book by Lindsay and Crouse. Based on the memoir The Story of the Trapp Family Singers by Maria von Trapp, the film is about a young Austrian postulant in Salzburg, Austria, in 1938 who is sent to the villa of a retired naval officer and widower to be governess to his seven children. After bringing love and music into the lives of the family, she marries the officer and, together with the children, finds a way to survive the loss of their homeland to the Nazis.
The film was released on March 2, 1965, in the United States, initially as a limited roadshow theatrical release. Although critical response to the film was mixed, the film was a major commercial success, becoming the number one box office movie after four weeks, and the highest-grossing film of 1965. By November 1966, The Sound of Music had become the highest-grossing film of all-time—surpassing Gone with the Wind—and held that distinction for five years. The film was just as popular throughout the world, breaking previous box-office records in twenty-nine countries. Following an initial theatrical release that lasted four and a half years, and two successful re-releases, the film sold 283 million admissions worldwide and earned a total worldwide gross of $286,000,000.
The Sound of Music received five Academy Awards, including Best Picture and Best Director. The film also received two Golden Globe Awards, for Best Motion Picture and Best Actress, the Directors Guild of America Award for Outstanding Directorial Achievement, and the Writers Guild of America Award for Best Written American Musical. In 1998, the American Film Institute (AFI) listed The Sound of Music as the fifty-fifth greatest American movie of all time, and the fourth greatest movie musical. In 2001, the United States Library of Congress selected the film for preservation in the National Film Registry, finding it ""culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant"".","{1025, 2051, 515, 4611, 7, 2568, 4134, 1576, 4671, 1095, 2122, 4682, 595, 1622, 2141, 608, 3180, 1646, 1136, 1649, 2169, 2682, 2171, 127, 640, 4736, 1678, 2703, 3727, 1177, 4768, 2721, 2210, 174, 1710, 1739, 4815, 3795, 4307, 3799, 3803, 3812, 748, 3322, 3842, 1795, 3348, 3862, 4895, 3874, 4905, 4400, 1847, 4920, 826, 2875, 3908, 4430, 2388, 1888, 1890, 873, 4971, 1388, 3951, 889, 4474, 3451, 892, 4990, 4993, 4994, 387, 3459, 2955, 3979, 1938, 1432, 4007, 5033, 2475, 2483, 4020, 4024, 1979, 4539, 3520, 1985, 452, 3524, 1990, 967, 4549, 971, 2507, 1997, 5074, 467, 4051, 5077, 2525, 1502, 2018, 997, 4589, 4605}",106,"['The Sound of Music', 'Julie Andrews', 'Christopher Plummer', 'Academy Awards Best Picture 1966', '1965', 'American', 'Robert Wise', 'Julie Andrews', 'Christopher Plummer', 'Richard Haydn', 'Eleanor Parker', '1959', 'Richard Rodgers', 'Oscar Hammerstein II', 'Ernest Lehman', 'Lindsay', 'Crouse', 'The Story of the Trapp Family Singers', 'Maria von Trapp', 'Austrian', 'Salzburg', 'Austria', '1938', 'Nazis', 'March 2, 1965', 'the United States', 'four weeks', '1965', 'November 1966', 'The Sound of Music', 'five years', 'four and a half years', 'The Sound of Music', 'Academy Awards', 'Best Picture and Best Director', 'America', 'the Writers Guild of America Award for Best Written American Musical', '1998', 'the American Film Institute', 'AFI', 'The Sound of Music', 'American', '2001', 'the United States', 'Congress', 'the National Film Registry']","['WORK_OF_ART', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'ORG', 'LAW', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'ORG']"
11,1965,April,28,"Barbra Streisand stars on ""My Name is Barbra"" special on CBS",https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbra_Streisand,"Barbara Joan ""Barbra"" Streisand (; born April 24, 1942) is an American singer, actress, and filmmaker. In a career spanning six decades, she has achieved success in multiple fields of entertainment and has been recognized with two Academy Awards, ten Grammy Awards including the Grammy Lifetime Achievement Award and the Grammy Legend Award, five Emmy Awards including one Daytime Emmy, a Special Tony Award, an American Film Institute award, a Kennedy Center Honors prize, four Peabody Awards, the Presidential Medal of Freedom, and nine Golden Globes. She is among a small group of entertainers who have been honored with an Emmy, Grammy, Oscar, and Tony Award – though only three were competitive awards – and is one of only two artists in that group who have also won a Peabody.After beginning a successful recording career in the 1960s, Streisand ventured into film by the end of that decade. She starred in the critically acclaimed Funny Girl, for which she won the Academy Award and Golden Globe Award for Best Actress. Her other films include The Owl and the Pussycat, The Way We Were, and A Star Is Born, for which she received her second Academy Award, composing music for the love theme ""Evergreen"", the first woman to be honored as a composer. With the release of Yentl in 1983, Streisand became the first woman to write, produce, direct, and star in a major studio film. The film won an Oscar for Best Score and a Golden Globe for Best Motion Picture Musical. Streisand also received the Golden Globe Award for Best Director, becoming the first (and to date only) woman to win that award.
Streisand is one of the best-selling recording artists of all time, with more than 68.5 million albums in the U.S. and with a total of 150 million records sold worldwide making her the best-selling female artist among top-selling artists recognized by the Recording Industry Association of America (RIAA). The RIAA and Billboard recognize Streisand as holding the record for the most top 10 albums of any female recording artist: a total of 34 since 1963. According to Billboard, she holds the record for the female with the most number one albums (11). Billboard also recognizes her as the greatest female of all time on its 200 chart and one of the greatest artists of all time on its Hot 100 chart. Streisand is the only recording artist to have a number-one album in each of the last six decades, having released 53 gold albums, 31 platinum albums, and 14 multi-platinum albums in the United States.","{1026, 4611, 2568, 524, 4134, 1576, 1583, 1081, 4671, 2122, 1622, 2647, 1633, 1133, 1649, 2169, 2171, 640, 1153, 4736, 1162, 2703, 3727, 4768, 2210, 174, 1711, 690, 4287, 3777, 1228, 4815, 3795, 4307, 1251, 2793, 2794, 748, 1795, 1288, 3348, 4895, 290, 3874, 1319, 4905, 4400, 1847, 826, 2875, 2379, 2901, 4971, 1388, 2415, 3951, 4474, 4990, 4993, 386, 4994, 2955, 3989, 1432, 418, 4516, 4007, 5033, 4020, 4024, 2489, 1979, 452, 4549, 1990, 971, 2507, 5067, 5077, 2525, 2018, 1508, 2026, 1526, 4605}",85,"['Barbra Streisand', 'My Name', 'CBS', 'Barbara Joan', 'April 24, 1942', 'American', 'six decades', 'Academy Awards', 'Daytime Emmy', 'Tony Award', 'American Film Institute', 'Kennedy Center Honors', 'Peabody Awards', 'the Presidential Medal of Freedom', 'Emmy', 'Grammy', 'Oscar', 'Tony Award', 'the 1960s', 'Streisand', 'the end of that decade', 'Funny Girl', 'the Academy Award', 'Golden Globe Award', 'The Owl and the Pussycat', 'The Way We Were', 'A Star Is Born', 'Academy Award', 'Evergreen', 'Yentl', '1983', 'Streisand', 'Streisand', 'the Golden Globe Award for Best Director', 'U.S.', 'the Recording Industry Association of America', 'RIAA', 'RIAA', 'Billboard', 'Streisand', '1963', 'Billboard', 'Billboard', 'Streisand', 'the last six decades', 'the United States']","['ORG', 'PRODUCT', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'FAC', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'LOC', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE']"
12,1965,February,6,"Righteous Brothers ""You've Lost That Lovin' Feelin'"" hits #1",https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You%27ve_Lost_That_Lovin%27_Feelin%27,"""You've Lost That Lovin' Feelin'"" is a song written by Phil Spector, Barry Mann, and Cynthia Weil. It was first recorded by the Righteous Brothers in 1964, produced by Phil Spector. Their recording is considered by some music critics to be the ultimate expression and illustration of Spector's ""Wall of Sound"" recording technique.  It has also been described by various music writers as ""one of the best records ever made"" and ""the ultimate pop record"".The original Righteous Brothers version was a critical and commercial success on its release, becoming a number-one hit single in both the United States and the United Kingdom in February 1965. It was the fifth best selling song of 1965 in the US.  It also entered the Top 10 in the UK chart on an unprecedented three separate occasions.""You've Lost That Lovin' Feelin'"" has been covered successfully by numerous artists. In 1965, Cilla Black's recording reached number two in the UK Singles Chart. Dionne Warwick took her version to number 16 on the Billboard Hot 100 chart in 1969. A 1971 duet version by singers Roberta Flack and Donny Hathaway peaked at number 30 on the Billboard R&B singles chart.  Long John Baldry charted at number two in Australia with his 1979 remake and a 1980 version by Hall and Oates reached number 12 on the US Hot 100.
In December 1999, the performing-rights organization Broadcast Music, Inc. (BMI) ranked the song as the most-played song on American radio and television in the 20th century, having accumulated more than 8 million airplays by 1999, and nearly 15 million by 2011. It held the distinction as the most-played song for 22 years until 2019. The song was chosen as one of the Songs of the Century by RIAA and ranked No. 34 on the list of the 500 Greatest Songs of All Time by Rolling Stone. In 2015, the single was inducted into the National Recording Registry by the Library of Congress for being ""culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant"".","{1378, 4741}",2,"['Feelin', 'Phil Spector', 'Barry Mann', 'Cynthia Weil', 'the Righteous Brothers', '1964', 'Phil Spector', 'Spector', 'Wall of Sound', 'Righteous Brothers', 'the United States', 'the United Kingdom', 'February 1965', '1965', 'US', 'UK', 'Feelin', '1965', ""Cilla Black's"", 'UK', 'Dionne Warwick', 'Billboard Hot 100', '1969', '1971', 'Roberta Flack', 'Donny Hathaway', 'Billboard R&B', 'Long John Baldry', 'Australia', '1979', '1980', 'Hall and Oates', 'December 1999', 'Broadcast Music,', 'American', 'the 20th century', '1999', '2011', '22 years', '2019', 'the Songs of the Century', 'RIAA', 'the 500 Greatest Songs of All Time by Rolling Stone', '2015', 'the National Recording Registry', 'Congress']","['PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'PRODUCT', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'ORG', 'EVENT', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG']"
13,1965,April,26,"Charles Ives' 4th Symphony premieres at Carnegie Hall, New York, 11 years after the composer's death",https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Ives,"Charles Edward Ives (; October 20, 1874 – May 19, 1954) was an American modernist composer, one of the first American composers of international renown. His music was largely ignored during his early life, and many of his works went unperformed for many years. Later in life, the quality of his music was publicly recognized, and he came to be regarded as an ""American original"". He was also among the first composers to engage in a systematic program of experimental music, with musical techniques including polytonality, polyrhythm, tone clusters, aleatory elements, and quarter tones. His experimentation foreshadowed many musical innovations that were later more widely adopted during the 20th century. Hence, he is often regarded as the leading American composer of art music of the 20th century.Sources of Ives' tonal imagery included hymn tunes and traditional songs; he also incorporated melodies of the town band at holiday parade, the fiddlers at Saturday night dances, patriotic songs, sentimental parlor ballads, and the melodies of Stephen Foster.","{2051, 1539, 4611, 7, 2568, 4642, 4134, 1576, 1583, 4671, 589, 3151, 4688, 595, 2647, 2141, 1633, 3686, 1640, 3693, 1646, 1136, 2169, 2682, 127, 4224, 1153, 1668, 1162, 1678, 1167, 2702, 1177, 4775, 1192, 694, 1739, 4307, 3803, 1251, 3812, 3813, 2793, 2794, 748, 1780, 3322, 1275, 3842, 1795, 1288, 1802, 3862, 4910, 1847, 4920, 826, 4426, 1867, 2379, 2891, 4430, 2388, 2901, 3927, 1888, 1890, 3427, 873, 1388, 2415, 889, 3451, 892, 4990, 387, 3459, 2955, 3979, 2964, 1432, 418, 4007, 5033, 2483, 948, 4024, 1985, 3524, 1990, 967, 2507, 1997, 4051, 5088, 1508, 997, 2026, 4589, 1526}",100,"[""Charles Ives'"", 'Carnegie Hall', 'New York', '11 years', 'Charles Edward Ives', 'October 20, 1874', 'May 19, 1954', 'American', 'American', 'many years', 'American', 'the 20th century', 'American', 'the 20th century', 'Saturday', 'Stephen Foster']","['PERSON', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON']"
14,1965,June,15,"Bob Dylan records single ""Like a Rolling Stone"" (#1 in Rolling Stone magazine's ""500 Greatest Songs of All Time"")",https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Like_a_Rolling_Stone,"""Like a Rolling Stone"" is a 1965 song by the American singer-songwriter Bob Dylan. Its confrontational lyrics originated in an extended piece of verse Dylan wrote in June 1965, when he returned exhausted from a grueling tour of England. Dylan distilled this draft into four verses and a chorus. ""Like a Rolling Stone"" was recorded a few weeks later as part of the sessions for the forthcoming album Highway 61 Revisited.
During a difficult two-day preproduction, Dylan struggled to find the essence of the song, which was demoed without success in 34 time. A breakthrough was made when it was tried in a rock music format, and rookie session musician Al Kooper improvised the organ riff for which the track is known. However, Columbia Records was unhappy with both the song's length at over six minutes and its heavy electric sound, and was hesitant to release it. It was only when a month later a copy was leaked to a new popular music club and heard by influential DJs that the song was put out as a single. Although radio stations were reluctant to play such a long track, ""Like a Rolling Stone"" reached No. 2 in the US Billboard charts (No. 1 in Cashbox) and became a worldwide hit.
Critics have described the track as revolutionary in its combination of different musical elements, the youthful, cynical sound of Dylan's voice, and the directness of the question ""How does it feel?"" ""Like a Rolling Stone"" completed the transformation of Dylan's image from folk singer to rock star, and is considered one of the most influential compositions in postwar popular music. According to review aggregator Acclaimed Music, ""Like a Rolling Stone"" is the statistically most acclaimed song of all time. Rolling Stone magazine listed the song at No. 1 in their ""500 Greatest Songs of All Time"" list. The song has been covered by numerous artists, from the Jimi Hendrix Experience and the Rolling Stones to the Wailers and Green Day. At an auction in 2014, Dylan's handwritten lyrics to the song fetched $2 million, a world record for a popular music manuscript.","{4101, 2078, 1573, 4134, 4647, 1583, 2096, 2122, 4682, 4688, 3154, 595, 3666, 619, 2155, 3180, 3693, 1136, 1653, 2169, 2170, 2682, 640, 1153, 131, 4741, 3207, 4750, 4758, 4768, 2210, 677, 173, 690, 2764, 717, 3277, 4815, 3795, 4307, 4313, 3805, 744, 2794, 748, 2798, 4859, 3842, 1795, 1808, 807, 4916, 309, 311, 1847, 4920, 4924, 2388, 4445, 1388, 2415, 889, 4474, 3451, 4990, 4993, 386, 387, 3460, 3970, 2955, 1422, 1938, 3989, 4007, 4014, 2995, 4539, 4549, 1990, 967, 5065, 971, 2507, 5074, 5077, 1502, 3040, 2018, 997, 4589, 5106, 1526}",93,"['Bob Dylan', 'Like a Rolling Stone', ""Rolling Stone magazine's"", 'Greatest Songs of All Time', 'Like a Rolling Stone', '1965', 'American', 'Bob Dylan', 'Dylan', 'June 1965', 'England', 'Dylan', 'a Rolling Stone', 'a few weeks later', 'two-day', 'Dylan', 'Al Kooper', 'Columbia Records', 'a month later', 'Like a Rolling Stone', 'US', 'Cashbox', 'Dylan', 'Like a Rolling Stone', 'Dylan', 'Like a Rolling Stone', 'Rolling Stone', 'Greatest Songs of All Time', 'the Jimi Hendrix Experience', 'the Rolling Stones', 'Wailers', 'Green Day', '2014', 'Dylan']","['PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'ORG', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'ORG', 'EVENT', 'LOC', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'ORG']"
15,1965,July,25,"Bob Dylan is booed by sections of the crowd at the Newport Folk Festival for performing with an electric guitar, beginning of folk-rock",https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Folk_rock,"Folk rock is a hybrid music genre combining elements of folk music and rock music, which arose in the United States, Canada, and the United Kingdom in the mid-1960s. In the U.S., folk rock emerged from the folk music revival and the influence that the Beatles and other British Invasion bands had on members of that movement. Performers such as Bob Dylan and the Byrds—several of whose members had earlier played in folk ensembles—attempted to blend the sounds of rock with their pre-existing folk repertoire, adopting the use of electric instrumentation and drums in a way previously discouraged in the U.S. folk community. The term ""folk rock"" was initially used in the U.S. music press in June 1965 to describe the Byrds' music.
The commercial success of the Byrds' cover version of Dylan's ""Mr. Tambourine Man"" and their debut album of the same name, along with Dylan's own recordings with rock instrumentation—on the albums Bringing It All Back Home (1965), Highway 61 Revisited (1965), and Blonde on Blonde (1966)—encouraged other folk acts, such as Simon & Garfunkel, to use electric backing on their records and new groups, such as Buffalo Springfield, to form. Dylan's controversial appearance at the Newport Folk Festival on 25 July 1965, where he was backed by an electric band, was also a pivotal moment in the development of the genre.
During the late 1960s in Britain and Europe, a distinct, eclectic British folk rock style was created by Pentangle, Fairport Convention and Alan Stivell. Inspired by British psychedelic folk and the North American style of folk rock, British folk rock bands began to incorporate elements of traditional British folk music into their repertoire, leading to other variants, including the overtly English folk rock of the Albion Band and Celtic rock.","{3842, 4611, 1795, 3459, 3970, 7, 2568, 2955, 4235, 5010, 278, 1432, 2169, 2210, 3365, 3621, 1319, 1576, 4775, 3882, 2171, 1711, 4400, 4785, 826, 1979, 2621, 4413, 703, 4671, 580, 3268, 583, 3322, 75, 4558, 4307, 2004, 2388, 4437, 4563, 4445, 4829, 744, 4986, 4330, 4971, 748, 1133, 4589, 3186, 4472, 889, 3578, 3451, 4605, 4990}",57,"['Bob Dylan', 'the Newport Folk Festival', 'the United States', 'Canada', 'the United Kingdom', 'the mid-1960s', 'U.S.', 'Beatles', 'British', 'Bob Dylan', 'Byrds', 'U.S.', 'U.S.', 'June 1965', 'Byrds', 'Byrds', 'Dylan', 'Tambourine Man', 'Dylan', 'Bringing It All Back Home', '1965', 'Blonde', 'Blonde', 'Simon & Garfunkel', 'Buffalo Springfield', 'Dylan', 'the Newport Folk Festival', '25 July 1965', 'the late 1960s', 'Britain', 'Europe', 'British', 'Pentangle', 'Alan Stivell', 'British', 'North American', 'British', 'British', 'English', 'the Albion Band', 'Celtic']","['PERSON', 'EVENT', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'EVENT', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'LOC', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'LANGUAGE', 'ORG', 'NORP']"
16,1965,September,2,Cubs slugger Ernie Banks hits his MLB 400th career HR (off Curt Simmons) in Chicago's 5-3 win v St. Louis at Wrigley Field; Simmons also gave up Willie Mays' 400th HR in 1963,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2009_in_baseball,The following are the baseball events of the year 2009  throughout the world.,set(),0,"['Cubs', 'Ernie Banks', 'Curt Simmons', 'Chicago', 'St. Louis', 'Wrigley Field', ""Willie Mays'"", '400th HR', '1963', 'the year 2009']","['ORG', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'FAC', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE']"
17,1965,September,18,"Mickey Mantle Day at Yankee Stadium: Mantle play his 2,000th game",https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mickey_Mantle,"Mickey Charles Mantle (October 20, 1931 – August 13, 1995), nicknamed The Commerce Comet and The Mick, was an American professional baseball player. Mantle played his entire Major League Baseball (MLB) career (1951–1968) with the New York Yankees as a center fielder, right fielder, and first baseman. Mantle was one of the best players and sluggers and is regarded by many as the greatest switch hitter in baseball history. Mantle was inducted into the Baseball Hall of Fame in 1974 and was elected to the Major League Baseball All-Century Team in 1999.
Mantle was one of the greatest offensive threats of any center fielder in baseball history. He has the second highest career OPS+ among center fielders, (behind Mike Trout) and he had the highest stolen base percentage in history at the time of his retirement. In addition, compared to the other four center fielders on the All-Century team, he had the lowest career rate of grounding into double plays, and he had the highest World Series on-base percentage and World Series slugging percentage. He also had an excellent .984 fielding percentage when playing center field. Mantle was noted for his ability to hit for both average and power, especially tape measure home runs, a term that was originated by a play-by-play caller reacting to one of Mantle's 1953 home runs. He hit 536 MLB career home runs, batted .300 or more ten times, and is the career leader (tied with Jim Thome) in walk-off home runs, with thirteen — twelve in the regular season, one in the postseason.
Mantle is 16th all-time in Home runs per at bats. He is 18th in on-base percentage . He was safe three out of four times he attempted to steal a base. He won the MVP Award three times, came in second three times, and came within nine votes of winning five times.
Mantle won the Triple Crown in 1956, when he led the major leagues in batting average (.353), home runs (52), and runs batted in (RBI) (130). He later wrote a  book (My Favorite Summer 1956) about his best year in baseball. He was an All-Star for 16 seasons, playing in 16 of the 20 All-Star Games that were played during his career. He was an American League (AL) Most Valuable Player (MVP) three times and a Gold Glove winner once. Mantle appeared in 12 World Series including seven championships, and he holds World Series records for the most home runs (18), RBIs (40), extra-base hits (26), runs (42), walks (43), and total bases (123).","{260, 3332, 1929, 778, 400, 145, 5010, 3091, 661, 663, 793, 2717, 4516, 1190, 1711, 2480, 2487, 1464, 58, 4287, 3777, 580, 1605, 328, 5070, 3676, 1373, 2525, 2172}",29,"['Mickey Mantle Day', 'Yankee Stadium:', 'Mickey Charles Mantle', 'October 20, 1931', 'August 13, 1995', 'The Commerce Comet', 'The Mick', 'American', 'Mantle', 'Major League Baseball', 'the New York Yankees', 'Mantle', 'Mantle', 'the Baseball Hall of Fame', '1974', 'the Major League Baseball All-Century Team', '1999', 'OPS+', 'Mike Trout', 'All-Century', 'World Series', 'World Series', 'Mantle', 'Mantle', '1953', 'Jim Thome', 'the regular season', 'the MVP Award three times', '1956', 'RBI', '(My Favorite Summer 1956', '16 seasons', 'American League (AL', 'Mantle', 'World Series', 'World Series']","['PERSON', 'FAC', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'EVENT', 'EVENT', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'EVENT', 'EVENT']"
18,1965,January,1,Novelist Michael Crichton (22) weds high school sweetheart Joan Radam,,,"{33, 4967, 3978, 2508, 815, 176, 463, 2169, 703}",9,"['Michael Crichton', '22', 'Joan Radam']","['PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON']"
19,1965,February,11,Beatle Ringo Starr marries Maureen Cox,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maureen_Starkey_Tigrett,"Maureen ""Mo"" Starkey Tigrett (born Mary Cox; 4 August 1946 – 30 December 1994) was a hairdresser from Liverpool, England, best known as the first wife of Ringo Starr, the Beatles' drummer. When she was a trainee hairdresser in Liverpool, she met Starr at The Cavern Club, where the Beatles were playing. Starr proposed marriage at the Ad-Lib Club in London, on 20 January 1965. They married at the Caxton Hall Register Office, London, in 1965, and divorced in 1975.
First living at 34 Montagu Square, Marylebone, the Starrs bought Sunny Heights, in St George's Hill, Weybridge. In 1973, they bought Tittenhurst Park from John Lennon. They had three children together: sons Zak and Jason, and daughter Lee. As a favour to Starr, Frank Sinatra taped a special version of ""The Lady Is a Tramp"" re-written by Sammy Cahn for Maureen's 22nd birthday in 1968.","{0, 636, 258, 260, 2182, 392, 776, 1929, 1547, 1676, 655, 2576, 145, 2196, 150, 1174, 412, 797, 678, 2856, 683, 1199, 1844, 5051, 316, 2751, 705, 4677, 1482, 2252, 3916, 2768, 984, 216, 1880, 2264, 994, 3430, 4841, 1772, 3182, 3444, 1269, 508}",44,"['Beatle Ringo Starr', 'Maureen Cox', 'Maureen ""Mo"" Starkey Tigrett', 'Mary Cox', '4 August 1946', 'December 1994', 'Liverpool', 'England', 'Ringo Starr', 'Beatles', 'Liverpool', 'Starr', 'The Cavern Club', 'Beatles', 'Starr', 'the Ad-Lib Club', 'London', '20 January 1965', 'the Caxton Hall Register Office', 'London', '1965', '1975', '34 Montagu Square', 'Marylebone', 'Starrs', 'Sunny Heights', ""St George's"", 'Weybridge', '1973', 'Tittenhurst Park', 'John Lennon', 'Zak', 'Jason', 'Lee', 'Starr', 'Frank Sinatra', 'The Lady Is a Tramp', 'Sammy Cahn', 'Maureen', '1968']","['PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'FAC', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'FAC', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'DATE']"
20,1965,March,26,Playwright Tom Stoppard (28) weds nurse Josie Ingle,,,"{4480, 290, 2210, 900, 4134, 3978, 4971, 2000, 4307, 3989, 4024, 2169, 3451}",13,"['Playwright Tom Stoppard', 'Josie Ingle']","['PERSON', 'PERSON']"
21,1966,January,19,Indira Gandhi elected India's 4th Prime Minister,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_prime_ministers_of_India,"The Prime Minister of India is the chief executive of the Government of India. In India's parliamentary system, the Constitution names the President as head of state de jure, but his or her de facto executive powers are vested in the prime minister and their Council of Ministers. Appointed and sworn-in by the President, the prime minister is usually the leader of the party or alliance that has a majority in the Lok Sabha, the lower house of Parliament of India.Since 1947 India has had 14 prime ministers, 15 including Gulzarilal Nanda who twice acted in the role of which 6 having at least one full term, ruling country for about 60 years. The first was Jawaharlal Nehru of the Indian National Congress party, who was sworn in on 15 August 1947, when India gained independence from the British Raj. Serving until his death in May 1964, Nehru remains India's longest-serving prime minister. He was succeeded by fellow Congressman Lal Bahadur Shastri, whose 19-month term also ended in death. Indira Gandhi, Nehru's daughter, succeeded Shastri in 1966 to become the country's first woman prime minister. Eleven years later, she was voted out of power in favour of the Janata Party, whose leader Morarji Desai became the first non-Congress prime minister. After he resigned in 1979, his former deputy Charan Singh briefly held office until Indira Gandhi was voted back six months later. Her second stint as prime minister ended five years later on 31 October 1984, when she was assassinated by her own bodyguards. Her son Rajiv Gandhi was then sworn in as India's youngest premier and the third from his family. Members of Nehru–Gandhi family have been prime minister for a total of 37 years and 303 days.Rajiv's five-year term ended with his former cabinet colleague, V. P. Singh of the Janata Dal, forming the year-long National Front coalition government in 1989. A seven-month interlude under prime minister Chandra Shekhar followed, after which the Congress party returned to power, forming the government under P. V. Narasimha Rao in June 1991. Rao's five-year term was succeeded by four short-lived governments—Atal Bihari Vajpayee from the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) for 13 days in 1996, a year each under United Front prime ministers H. D. Deve Gowda and I. K. Gujral, and Vajpayee again for 19 months in 1998–99. After Vajpayee was sworn-in for the third time, in 1999, he managed to lead his National Democratic Alliance (NDA) government to a full five-year term, the first non-Congress alliance to do so. Vajpayee was succeeded by Manmohan Singh, whose United Progressive Alliance government was in office for 10 years between 2004 and 2014. The incumbent prime minister of India is Narendra Modi who has headed the BJP-led NDA government since 26 May 2014 which is India's first non-Congress single party majority government.","{2051, 4101, 4614, 7, 523, 3597, 536, 539, 2080, 3110, 4134, 2088, 1583, 561, 1591, 2122, 4682, 3154, 595, 3666, 2141, 606, 607, 608, 3581, 3180, 3693, 1646, 1136, 3190, 2169, 2682, 1153, 2695, 1162, 2187, 1682, 4756, 4758, 1177, 4768, 2210, 4770, 680, 4776, 1710, 202, 1739, 4815, 3795, 4307, 3799, 3803, 3812, 234, 2794, 748, 3834, 3326, 3842, 273, 3862, 4374, 4891, 3877, 2864, 4402, 2355, 334, 847, 4430, 2391, 4445, 1888, 873, 3434, 4971, 1388, 2415, 370, 1908, 4474, 4476, 3970, 387, 4483, 3989, 413, 418, 4007, 2995, 4539, 4549, 1990, 967, 971, 2507, 5074, 467, 3542, 2018, 1508, 4589, 3574, 4603, 5117}",106,"['Indira Gandhi', 'India', 'India', 'the Government of India', 'India', 'Constitution', 'their Council of Ministers', 'the Lok Sabha', 'Parliament of India', '1947', 'India', 'Gulzarilal Nanda', 'about 60 years', 'Jawaharlal', 'the Indian National Congress party', '15 August 1947', 'India', 'British', 'May 1964', 'India', 'Lal Bahadur Shastri', 'Indira Gandhi', 'Nehru', 'Shastri', '1966', 'Eleven years later', 'the Janata Party', 'Morarji Desai', '1979', 'Charan Singh', 'Indira Gandhi', 'six months later', 'five years later', '31 October 1984', 'Rajiv Gandhi', 'India', 'Nehru', 'Gandhi', '37 years', '303 days', 'Rajiv', 'five-year', 'V. P. Singh', 'the Janata Dal', 'year-long', 'National Front', '1989', 'seven-month', 'Chandra Shekhar', 'the Congress party', 'P. V. Narasimha Rao', 'June 1991', 'five-year', 'the Bharatiya Janata Party', 'BJP', '13 days in 1996', 'a year', 'United Front', 'H. D. Deve Gowda', 'I. K. Gujral', 'Vajpayee', '19 months', '1998–99', 'Vajpayee', '1999', 'National Democratic Alliance', 'NDA', 'five-year', 'Vajpayee', 'Manmohan Singh', 'United Progressive Alliance', '10 years between 2004 and 2014', 'India', 'Narendra Modi', 'BJP', 'NDA', 'May 2014', 'India']","['PERSON', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'LAW', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE']"
22,1966,February,3,1st soft landing on Moon (Soviet Luna 9),https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_missions_to_the_Moon,"As part of human exploration of the Moon, numerous space missions have been undertaken to study Earth's natural satellite. Of the Moon landings, Luna 2 of the Soviet Union was the first spacecraft to reach its surface successfully, intentionally impacting the Moon on 13 September 1959. In 1966, Luna 9 became the first spacecraft to achieve a controlled soft landing, while Luna 10 became the first mission to enter orbit.
Between 1968 and 1972, crewed missions to the Moon were conducted by the United States as part of the Apollo program. Apollo 8 was the first crewed mission to enter orbit in December 1968, and was followed by Apollo 10 in May 1969. Six missions landed men on the Moon, beginning with Apollo 11 in July 1969, during which Neil Armstrong became the first man to walk on the Moon. Apollo 13 was intended to land, however it was restricted to a flyby due to a malfunction aboard the spacecraft. All nine crewed missions returned safely to the Earth.
While the United States focused on the crewed Apollo program, the Soviet Union conducted uncrewed missions that deployed rovers and returned samples to the Earth. Three rover missions were launched, of which two were successful, and eleven sample return flights were attempted with three successes.
Missions to the Moon have been conducted by the Soviet Union, United States, European Space Agency, Japan, India, People's Republic of China, Luxembourg and Israel. The Moon has also been visited by five spacecraft not dedicated to studying it; four spacecraft have flown past it to gain gravity assistance, and a radio telescope, Explorer 49, was placed into selenocentric orbit in order to use the Moon to block interference from terrestrial radio sources.","{7, 528, 28, 3612, 4642, 4140, 565, 1591, 2104, 1081, 4675, 580, 1095, 3154, 595, 2645, 2137, 603, 608, 609, 3692, 3702, 2171, 128, 4235, 4770, 1703, 1192, 1197, 4785, 703, 704, 1222, 2763, 717, 1746, 4307, 2261, 4829, 3814, 743, 3322, 3842, 3864, 1832, 3882, 3885, 4915, 4413, 2884, 839, 843, 4430, 2388, 854, 4951, 1370, 352, 4971, 370, 375, 889, 4986, 4477, 3970, 900, 2948, 903, 1931, 2955, 4492, 1938, 2964, 2982, 423, 430, 4536, 442, 1979, 4547, 452, 1483, 463, 1999, 4561, 2514, 2004, 3046, 4074, 494, 1017, 3578, 4605}",93,"['1st', 'Moon', 'Moon', 'Earth', 'Moon', 'the Soviet Union', 'Moon', '13 September 1959', '1966', 'Between 1968 and 1972', 'Moon', 'the United States', 'Apollo', 'December 1968', 'Apollo', 'May 1969', 'Apollo', 'July 1969', 'Neil Armstrong', 'Moon', 'Earth', 'the United States', 'Apollo', 'the Soviet Union', 'Earth', 'Moon', 'the Soviet Union', 'United States', 'European Space Agency', 'Japan', 'India', ""People's Republic of China"", 'Luxembourg', 'Israel', 'Moon']","['DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'LOC', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'LOC', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'LOC', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'PERSON']"
23,1966,March,11,Military coup led by Indonesian General Suharto breaks out,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indonesian_mass_killings_of_1965%E2%80%9366,"The Indonesian mass killings of 1965–66 (Indonesian genocide, Indonesian Communist Purge, Indonesian politicide, or the 1965 Tragedy) (Indonesian: Pembunuhan Massal Indonesia & Pembersihan G.30.S/PKI) were large-scale killings and civil unrest that occurred in Indonesia over several months, targeting Communist Party of Indonesia (PKI) party members, Communist sympathisers, Gerwani women, ethnic Abangan Javanese, ethnic Chinese and alleged leftists, often at the instigation of the armed forces and government. It began as an anti-communist purge following a controversial attempted coup d'état by the 30 September Movement. The most widely published estimates were that 500,000 to more than one million people were killed, with some more recent estimates going as high as two to three million. The purge was a pivotal event in the transition to the ""New Order"" and the elimination of PKI as a political force, with impacts on the global Cold War. The upheavals led to the fall of President Sukarno and the commencement of Suharto's three-decade authoritarian presidency.
The claims of a coup attempt by Communists released pent-up communal hatreds; these were fanned by the Indonesian Army, which quickly blamed the PKI. Communists were purged from political, social, and military life, and the PKI itself was disbanded and banned. The massacres began in October 1965, in the weeks following the coup attempt, and reached their peak over the remainder of the year before subsiding in the early months of 1966. They started in the capital, Jakarta, and spread to Central and East Java, and later Bali. Thousands of local vigilantes and army units killed actual and alleged PKI members. Killings occurred across the country, with the worst in the PKI strongholds of Central Java, East Java, Bali, and northern Sumatra. It is possible that over one million people were imprisoned at one time or another.
Sukarno's balancing act of ""Nasakom"" (nationalism, religion and communism) had unravelled. His most significant pillar of support, the PKI, was effectively eliminated by the other two pillars—the army and political Islam; and the army was on the way to unchallenged power. In March 1967, Sukarno was stripped of his remaining power by Indonesia's provisional Parliament, and Suharto was named Acting President. In March 1968, Suharto was formally elected president.
The killings are skipped over in most Indonesian history textbooks and have received little introspection by Indonesians, due to their suppression under the Suharto regime. The search for satisfactory explanations for the scale and frenzy of the violence has challenged scholars from all ideological perspectives. The possibility of a return to similar upheavals is cited as a factor in the ""New Order"" administration's political conservatism and tight control of the political system. Vigilance and stigma against a perceived communist threat remained a hallmark of Suharto's doctrine, and it is still in force even today.Despite a consensus at the highest levels of the US and British governments that it would be necessary ""to liquidate Sukarno"", as related in a CIA memorandum from 1962, and the existence of extensive contacts between anti-communist army officers and the US military establishment – training of over 1,200 officers, ""including senior military figures"", and providing weapons and economic assistance – the CIA denied active involvement in the killings. Declassified US documents in 2017 revealed that the US government had detailed knowledge of the mass killings from the beginning, and was supportive of the actions of the Indonesian Army. US complicity in the killings, which included providing extensive lists of PKI officials to Indonesian death squads, has previously been established by historians and journalists. A top-secret CIA report from 1968 stated that the massacres ""rank as one of the worst mass murders of the 20th century, along with the Soviet purges of the 1930s, the Nazi mass murders during the Second World War, and the Maoist bloodbath of the early 1950s.""","{2051, 4101, 6, 523, 1555, 1559, 4123, 2080, 4643, 1573, 4134, 4647, 3625, 1583, 2096, 561, 2122, 4682, 4688, 595, 2141, 3167, 4199, 2155, 3180, 3693, 1136, 1653, 3702, 2170, 2171, 128, 640, 1153, 4736, 4741, 4758, 4255, 4768, 2721, 2210, 2217, 188, 4800, 202, 2764, 717, 3277, 4815, 3795, 4307, 4313, 3805, 3299, 1765, 2798, 3833, 4859, 3842, 1803, 269, 1299, 3877, 807, 4916, 309, 311, 1847, 4920, 1865, 2891, 2896, 1873, 1372, 861, 1888, 3434, 1388, 2415, 3951, 889, 4474, 4990, 895, 4480, 3457, 386, 387, 3460, 3970, 1414, 391, 3490, 1960, 4014, 2995, 4539, 1985, 4549, 967, 5065, 971, 2507, 5077, 3040, 2529, 3564, 5106, 1526, 504, 5117}",111,"['Indonesian', 'Suharto', 'Indonesian', 'Indonesian', 'Indonesian', 'Communist Purge', 'Indonesian', '1965', 'Tragedy', 'Indonesian', 'Pembunuhan Massal', 'Indonesia', 'several months', 'Communist Party of Indonesia', 'Communist', 'Gerwani', 'Abangan Javanese', 'Chinese', 'September Movement', 'the ""New Order""', 'Cold War', 'Sukarno', ""Suharto's"", 'three-decade', 'Communists', 'the Indonesian Army', 'Communists', 'PKI', 'October 1965', 'the weeks', 'the year', 'the early months of 1966', 'Jakarta', 'Central', 'Central Java', 'East Java', 'Bali', 'Nasakom', 'PKI', 'army', 'Islam', 'March 1967', 'Sukarno', 'Indonesia', 'Parliament', 'Suharto', 'Acting', 'March 1968', 'Suharto', 'Indonesian', 'Indonesians', 'Suharto', 'the ""New Order""', 'Vigilance', ""Suharto's"", 'today', 'US', 'British', 'Sukarno', 'CIA', '1962', 'US', 'CIA', 'US', '2017', 'US', 'the Indonesian Army', 'US', 'Indonesian', 'CIA', '1968', 'the 20th century', 'Soviet', 'the 1930s', 'Nazi', 'the Second World War', 'Maoist', 'the early 1950s']","['NORP', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'EVENT', 'ORG', 'EVENT', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'LOC', 'LOC', 'PERSON', 'PERSON', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'LOC', 'EVENT', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'LOC', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'EVENT', 'NORP', 'DATE']"
24,1966,March,26,"Large-scale anti-Vietnam War protests take place in the United States, including in New York, Washington, D.C. and Chicago",https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Opposition_to_United_States_involvement_in_the_Vietnam_War,"Opposition to United States involvement in the Vietnam War began with demonstrations in 1964 against the escalating role of the United States in the Vietnam War and grew into a broad social movement over the ensuing several years. This movement informed and helped shape the vigorous and polarizing debate, primarily in the United States, during the second half of the 1960s and early 1970s on how to end the war.
Many in the peace movement within the United States were students, mothers, or anti-establishment hippies. Opposition grew with participation by the African-American civil rights, women's liberation, Chicano Movements, and sectors of organized labor. Additional involvement came from many other groups, including educators, clergy, academics, journalists, lawyers, physicians—such as Benjamin Spock—and military veterans.
Their actions consisted mainly of peaceful, nonviolent events; few events were deliberately provocative and violent. In some cases, police used violent tactics against peaceful demonstrators. By 1967, according to Gallup polls, an increasing majority of Americans considered military involvement in Vietnam to be a mistake, echoed decades later by the then-head of American war planning, former Secretary of Defense Robert McNamara.","{1272, 3459, 1795, 2052, 3332, 7, 2568, 2955, 3979, 2066, 3091, 2964, 5010, 1307, 805, 1319, 1576, 3243, 3371, 1709, 3500, 1711, 4526, 563, 948, 4661, 1464, 1979, 4923, 4671, 2112, 4675, 580, 3524, 586, 2379, 3322, 1997, 4558, 2004, 3413, 4437, 3927, 3034, 4192, 3427, 3813, 4971, 748, 632, 889, 3578, 3195, 4605, 127}",55,"['the United States', 'New York', 'Washington', 'D.C.', 'Chicago', 'United States', 'the Vietnam War', '1964', 'the United States', 'the Vietnam War', 'several years', 'the United States', 'the second half of the 1960s', 'early 1970s', 'the United States', 'African-American', 'Chicano Movements', 'Benjamin Spock', '1967', 'Gallup', 'Americans', 'Vietnam', 'American', 'Defense', 'Robert McNamara']","['GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'EVENT', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'EVENT', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'PERSON']"
25,1966,June,29,Vietnam War: US planes bomb the North Vietnamese capital Hanoi and the port city of Haiphong for the first time,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vietnam_War,"The Vietnam War (Vietnamese: Chiến tranh Việt Nam), also known as the Second Indochina War, and in Vietnam as the Resistance War Against America (Vietnamese: Kháng chiến chống Mỹ) or simply the American War, was a conflict in Vietnam, Laos, and Cambodia from 1 November 1955 to the fall of Saigon on 30 April 1975. It was the second of the Indochina Wars and was officially fought between North Vietnam and South Vietnam. North Vietnam was supported by the Soviet Union, China, and other communist allies; South Vietnam was supported by the United States, South Korea, the Philippines, Australia, Thailand and other anti-communist allies. The war, considered a Cold War-era proxy war by some, lasted 19 years, with direct U.S. involvement ending in 1973, and included the Laotian Civil War and the Cambodian Civil War, which ended with all three countries becoming communist in 1975.
The conflict emerged from the First Indochina War against the communist-led Viet Minh. Most of the funding for the French war effort was provided by the U.S. After the French quit Indochina in 1954, the US assumed financial and military support for the South Vietnamese state. The Việt Cộng, also known as Front national de libération du Sud-Viêt Nam or NLF (the National Liberation Front), a South Vietnamese common front under the direction of North Vietnam, initiated a guerrilla war in the south. North Vietnam had also invaded Laos in the mid-1950s in support of insurgents, establishing the Ho Chi Minh Trail to supply and reinforce the Việt Cộng. U.S. involvement escalated under President John F. Kennedy through the MAAG program from just under a thousand military advisors in 1959 to 16,000 in 1963. By 1963, the North Vietnamese had sent 40,000 soldiers to fight in South Vietnam. North Vietnam was heavily backed by the USSR and the People's Republic of China. China also sent hundreds of PLA servicemen to North Vietnam to serve in air-defense and support roles.By 1964, there were 23,000 US advisors in South Vietnam. In August, the Gulf of Tonkin incident occurred, in which a U.S. destroyer was alleged to have clashed with North Vietnamese fast attack craft. In response, the U.S Congress passed the Gulf of Tonkin Resolution, giving President Lyndon B. Johnson broad authorization to increase U.S. military presence. He ordered the deployment of combat units for the first time and increased troop levels to 184,000. Past this point, the People's Army of Vietnam (PAVN) (also known as the North Vietnamese Army or NVA) engaged in more conventional warfare with U.S and South Vietnamese forces. Every year onward, there was significant build-up of U.S forces, despite little progress. U.S Secretary of Defense Robert McNamara, one of the principal architects of the war, began expressing doubts of victory by the end of 1966. U.S. and South Vietnam forces relied on air superiority and overwhelming firepower to conduct search and destroy operations, involving ground forces, artillery, and airstrikes. The U.S. also conducted a large-scale strategic bombing campaign against North Vietnam and Laos.
The Tet Offensive of 1968 showed the lack of progress with these doctrines. With the VC and PAVN mounting large-scale urban offensives throughout 1968, U.S domestic support for the war began fading. The Army of the Republic of Vietnam (ARVN) expanded following a period of neglect after Tet and was modeled after U.S doctrine. The VC sustained heavy losses during the Tet Offensive and subsequent U.S.-ARVN operations in the rest of 1968, losing over 50,000 men. The CIA's Phoenix Program further degraded the VC's membership and capabilities. By the end of the year, the VC insurgents held almost no territory in South Vietnam, and their recruitment dropped by over 80% in 1969, signifying a drastic reduction in guerrilla operations, necessitating increased use of PAVN regular soldiers from the north. In 1969, North Vietnam declared a Provisional Revolutionary Government in South Vietnam in an attempt to give the reduced VC a more international stature, but the southern guerrillas from then on were sidelined as PAVN forces begun more conventional Combined arms warfare. Operations crossed national borders: Laos was invaded by North Vietnam early on, while Cambodia was used by North Vietnam as a supply route starting in 1967; the route through Cambodia began to be bombed by the U.S. in 1969, while the Laos route had been heavily bombed since 1964. The deposing of the monarch Norodom Sihanouk by the Cambodian National Assembly resulted in a PAVN invasion of the country at the request of the Khmer Rouge, escalating the Cambodian Civil War and resulting in a U.S.-RVN counter-invasion.
In 1969, following the election of U.S President Richard Nixon, a policy of ""Vietnamization"" began, which saw the conflict fought by an expanded ARVN, with U.S. forces sidelined and increasingly demoralized by domestic opposition and reduced recruitment. U.S. ground forces had largely withdrawn by early 1972 and support was limited to air support, artillery support, advisers, and materiel shipments. The ARVN, buttressed by said U.S. support, stopped the largest and first mechanized PAVN offensive to date during the Easter Offensive of 1972.The offensive resulted in heavy casualties on both sides and the failure of the PAVN to subdue South Vietnam, but the ARVN itself failed to recapture all territory, leaving its military situation difficult. The Paris Peace Accords of January 1973 saw all U.S forces withdrawn; the Case–Church Amendment, passed by the U.S Congress on 15 August 1973, officially ended direct U.S military involvement. The Peace Accords were broken almost immediately, and fighting continued for two more years. Phnom Penh fell to the Khmer Rouge on 17 April 1975 while the 1975 Spring Offensive saw the capture of Saigon by the PAVN on 30 April; this marked the end of the war, and North and South Vietnam were reunified the following year.
The scale of fighting was enormous: by 1970 the ARVN was the world's fourth largest army, with the PAVN being similar in size at around a million regular soldiers. The war exacted a huge human cost in terms of fatalities (see Vietnam War casualties): estimates of the number of Vietnamese soldiers and civilians killed vary from 966,000 to 3.8 million. Some 275,000–310,000 Cambodians, 20,000–62,000 Laotians, and 58,220 U.S. service members also died in the conflict, and a further 1,626 remain missing in action.The Sino-Soviet split re-emerged following the lull during the Vietnam War. Conflict between North Vietnam and its Cambodian allies in the Royal Government of the National Union of Kampuchea, and the newly-formed Democratic Kampuchea begun almost immediately in a series of border raids by the Khmer Rouge, eventually escalating into the Cambodian–Vietnamese War. Chinese forces directly invaded Vietnam in the Sino-Vietnamese War, with subsequent border conflicts lasting until 1991. Insurgencies were fought by the unified Vietnam in all three countries. The end of the war and resumption of the Third Indochina War would precipitate the Vietnamese boat people and the larger Indochina refugee crisis, which saw millions of refugees leave Indochina (mainly southern Vietnam), with an estimated 250,000 of whom perished at sea. Within the U.S, the war gave rise to what was referred to as Vietnam Syndrome, a public aversion to American overseas military involvements, which together with the Watergate scandal contributed to the crisis of confidence that affected America throughout the 1970s.","{1026, 4611, 2051, 4101, 7, 2568, 521, 2058, 528, 3090, 20, 1562, 28, 2589, 2590, 2078, 1566, 4642, 1573, 4134, 4647, 1576, 2092, 3630, 2096, 563, 4661, 1081, 4671, 2112, 2628, 1095, 2122, 4682, 1616, 4688, 595, 2649, 2652, 2141, 608, 4704, 3686, 1642, 2155, 3180, 1133, 1646, 1136, 3184, 3186, 629, 1653, 2682, 3195, 2170, 2171, 640, 2176, 131, 4235, 1678, 2703, 3727, 1177, 3229, 4768, 2721, 2210, 2213, 2215, 3243, 4268, 1709, 1711, 4785, 1204, 3777, 3268, 1222, 1739, 2764, 717, 3277, 3795, 4307, 4313, 3803, 3804, 3805, 4829, 3298, 3812, 3303, 748, 2798, 1780, 1783, 1272, 3322, 1275, 4859, 3842, 1795, 3332, 1295, 1808, 278, 3862, 3869, 4895, 290, 4899, 807, 1319, 4905, 3371, 2861, 4400, 4916, 309, 310, 311, 1847, 4407, 826, 2875, 4924, 4413, 830, 2891, 4941, 4430, 4944, 3413, 3927, 1370, 352, 1888, 1890, 3427, 1386, 4971, 1388, 889, 4474, 3451, 892, 4990, 4993, 3970, 387, 3459, 3460, 4994, 1931, 2955, 3979, 401, 1938, 3989, 1432, 5019, 4007, 1960, 5033, 4014, 4526, 2483, 2995, 3508, 1979, 4539, 1985, 5059, 964, 3524, 1990, 967, 4549, 5065, 971, 2507, 1997, 2508, 5067, 467, 2004, 4051, 5077, 3544, 3034, 1502, 3040, 2018, 997, 5097, 492, 5106, 5110, 2039}",201,"['Vietnam', 'US', 'North Vietnamese', 'Hanoi', 'Haiphong', 'The Vietnam War', 'Vietnamese', 'Chiến', 'Việt Nam', 'the Second Indochina War', 'Vietnam', 'the Resistance War Against America', 'Vietnamese', 'Kháng', 'chống Mỹ', 'the American War', 'Vietnam', 'Laos', 'Cambodia', '1 November 1955', 'Saigon', '30 April 1975', 'the Indochina Wars', 'North Vietnam', 'South Vietnam', 'North Vietnam', 'the Soviet Union', 'China', 'South Vietnam', 'the United States', 'South Korea', 'Philippines', 'Australia', 'Thailand', 'Cold War-era', '19 years', 'U.S.', '1973', 'the Laotian Civil War', 'the Cambodian Civil War', '1975', 'the First Indochina War', 'Viet Minh', 'French', 'U.S.', 'French', 'Indochina', '1954', 'US', 'South Vietnamese', 'The Việt Cộng', 'Front national de libération du Sud-Viêt Nam', 'the National Liberation Front', 'South Vietnamese', 'North Vietnam', 'North Vietnam', 'Laos', 'the mid-1950s', 'U.S.', 'John F. Kennedy', '1959', '1963', '1963', 'the North Vietnamese', 'South Vietnam', 'North Vietnam', 'USSR', ""the People's Republic of China"", 'China', 'PLA', 'North Vietnam', '1964', 'US', 'South Vietnam', 'August', 'the Gulf of Tonkin', 'U.S.', 'North Vietnamese', 'the U.S Congress', 'the Gulf of Tonkin Resolution', 'Lyndon B. Johnson', 'U.S.', ""the People's Army"", 'Vietnam', 'PAVN', 'the North Vietnamese Army', 'NVA', 'U.S', 'South Vietnamese', 'U.S', 'U.S', 'Defense', 'Robert McNamara', 'the end of 1966', 'U.S.', 'South Vietnam', 'U.S.', 'North Vietnam', 'Laos', 'The Tet Offensive', '1968', 'VC', 'PAVN', '1968', 'U.S', 'The Army of the Republic of Vietnam', 'ARVN', 'Tet', 'U.S', 'VC', 'the Tet Offensive', '1968', 'CIA', 'Phoenix Program', 'VC', 'the end of the year', 'VC', 'South Vietnam', 'over 80%', '1969', 'PAVN', '1969', 'North Vietnam', 'Provisional Revolutionary Government', 'South Vietnam', 'VC', 'PAVN', 'Laos', 'North Vietnam', 'Cambodia', 'North Vietnam', '1967', 'Cambodia', 'U.S.', '1969', 'Laos', '1964', 'Norodom Sihanouk', 'the Cambodian National Assembly', 'PAVN', 'the Khmer Rouge', 'the Cambodian Civil War', 'U.S.-RVN', '1969', 'U.S', 'Richard Nixon', 'ARVN', 'U.S.', 'U.S.', 'early 1972', 'ARVN', 'U.S.', 'PAVN', 'the Easter Offensive', 'PAVN', 'South Vietnam', 'ARVN', 'The Paris Peace Accords', 'January 1973', 'U.S', 'Church Amendment', 'the U.S Congress', '15 August 1973', 'U.S', 'The Peace Accords', 'two more years', 'Phnom Penh', 'the Khmer Rouge', '17 April 1975', '1975', 'Spring Offensive', 'Saigon', 'PAVN', '30 April', 'North and', 'the following year', '1970', 'ARVN', 'PAVN', 'Vietnam War', 'Vietnamese', 'Cambodians', 'Laotians', 'U.S.', 'Sino', 'the Vietnam War', 'North Vietnam', 'Cambodian', 'the Royal Government of the National Union of Kampuchea', 'Democratic', 'Kampuchea', 'the Khmer Rouge', 'Cambodian', 'Vietnamese', 'Chinese', 'Vietnam', 'the Sino-Vietnamese War', '1991', 'Vietnam', 'the Third Indochina War', 'Vietnamese', 'Indochina', 'Indochina', 'Vietnam', 'U.S', 'Vietnam Syndrome', 'American', 'Watergate', 'America', 'the 1970s']","['GPE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'EVENT', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'EVENT', 'GPE', 'EVENT', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'EVENT', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'FAC', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'EVENT', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'EVENT', 'DATE', 'EVENT', 'LOC', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'WORK_OF_ART', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'LOC', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'LOC', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'EVENT', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'EVENT', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'PERCENT', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'EVENT', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'PRODUCT', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'LAW', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'LAW', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'LAW', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'EVENT', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'EVENT', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'PRODUCT', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'EVENT', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'EVENT', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'EVENT', 'NORP', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'NORP', 'EVENT', 'GPE', 'DATE']"
26,1966,July,13,A. C. Bhaktivedanta Swami Prabhupada founds the International Society for Krishna Consciousness (Hare Krishna movement) in New York City,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Society_for_Krishna_Consciousness,"The International Society for Krishna Consciousness (ISKCON), known colloquially as the Hare Krishna movement or Hare Krishnas, is a Gaudiya Vaishnava Hindu religious organisation. ISKCON was founded in 1966 in New York City by A. C. Bhaktivedanta Swami Prabhupada. Its core beliefs are based on the Hindu scriptures, particularly the Bhagavad Gita and the Bhagavata Purana, and the Gaudiya Vaishnava tradition, which has had adherents in India since the late 15th century and American and European devotees since the early 1900s.The organization was formed to spread the practice of Bhakti yoga, the practice of love of God in which those involved (bhaktas) dedicate their thoughts and actions towards pleasing Krishna, the Supreme Lord. Its most rapid expansions in membership as of 2007 have been within India and especially after the collapse of the Soviet Union, in Russia, Ukraine, and the rest of the ex-Soviet aligned states of Eastern Europe and Central Asia. The organization is banned in Singapore.Today, it has around a million congregational members worldwide including 15 000 in the United Kingdom as of June 2019, and despite the ""relatively small number of followers in the West (around a few thousand fulltime practitioners)"", it has been described as influential.The movement has been the subject of controversies. It has been labelled a cult by anti-cult organizations. It has also been called for banning in Bangladesh by the Hefazat-e-Islam organisation. In the 1990s ISKCON faced accusations of child abuse, and its leaders acknowledged physical, emotional and sexual abuse of children who were sent to live in the movement's boarding schools in the United States and India in the 1970s and 1980s. Several safety regulations and subcommittees, such as ISKCON Resolve and the ISKCON Child Protection Office, have been developed since these allegations to ensure that  legal rights as well as the health and safety of devotees are protected unconditionally.","{4611, 1539, 2052, 1031, 2568, 1038, 1041, 2579, 3091, 2069, 1562, 1563, 28, 1566, 33, 1058, 4642, 4643, 3621, 550, 1576, 1066, 4140, 1583, 1584, 563, 565, 1591, 2104, 4154, 4671, 576, 4675, 70, 2119, 3656, 586, 4688, 2131, 1109, 1622, 2647, 2649, 3676, 608, 97, 1633, 3682, 3686, 2152, 1133, 1137, 1649, 632, 2169, 2171, 3199, 640, 1153, 1162, 2703, 3727, 663, 1178, 3228, 1183, 4255, 2721, 2210, 4768, 4774, 1192, 1193, 2221, 1711, 176, 694, 4287, 3777, 2245, 198, 1740, 1235, 3795, 4307, 1240, 1251, 3299, 1765, 3811, 3814, 4324, 2793, 748, 1272, 3833, 767, 257, 1795, 3332, 4868, 1288, 1804, 269, 4879, 287, 4895, 3365, 1830, 1319, 4905, 3371, 4400, 2865, 311, 4407, 826, 2874, 2875, 4923, 2878, 1346, 2372, 1865, 4426, 843, 2891, 4940, 2382, 2896, 2898, 2388, 2901, 854, 3927, 4437, 1372, 861, 3427, 2916, 4971, 3437, 2415, 370, 885, 1397, 3451, 4990, 4480, 4993, 3970, 3459, 900, 4994, 4487, 2955, 3979, 5003, 5010, 403, 2964, 3989, 5019, 3489, 4516, 2982, 423, 5033, 1452, 4017, 948, 2487, 1464, 1466, 1979, 1471, 452, 964, 4549, 2504, 1997, 2509, 4558, 5077, 471, 1502, 3553, 1508, 3049, 2026, 1526, 1015, 504, 4601, 3578, 4605}",196,"['A. C. Bhaktivedanta Swami Prabhupada', 'the International Society for Krishna Consciousness', 'New York City', 'The International Society for Krishna Consciousness', 'ISKCON', 'Hare Krishna', 'Hare Krishnas', 'ISKCON', '1966', 'New York City', 'A. C. Bhaktivedanta Swami Prabhupada', 'Hindu', 'the Bhagavad Gita', 'the Bhagavata Purana', 'Gaudiya Vaishnava', 'India', 'the late 15th century', 'American', 'European', 'the early 1900s', 'Bhakti', 'Krishna', 'the Supreme Lord', '2007', 'India', 'the Soviet Union', 'Russia', 'Ukraine', 'ex-Soviet', 'Eastern Europe', 'Central Asia', 'Singapore', 'Today', 'the United Kingdom', 'June 2019', 'Bangladesh', 'the 1990s', 'ISKCON', 'the United States', 'India', 'the 1970s and 1980s', 'ISKCON Resolve', 'the ISKCON Child Protection Office']","['PERSON', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'PERSON', 'LOC', 'PERSON', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'ORG', 'ORG', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'NORP', 'LOC', 'LOC', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'GPE', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'ORG', 'ORG']"
27,1966,November,2,"The Cuban Adjustment Act comes into force, allowing 123,000 Cubans opportunity to apply for permanent residence in the US",https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/November_2,November 2 is the 306th day of the year (307th in leap years) in the Gregorian calendar.  59 days remain until the end of the year.,"{640, 2051, 2703, 1808, 1432, 1177, 4768, 418, 1573, 4134, 4647, 4014, 1583, 2096, 2483, 2995, 4916, 311, 4024, 2628, 4549, 967, 3272, 2122, 971, 2507, 3277, 4815, 4313, 2141, 3040, 2278, 234, 619, 1388, 2155, 2794, 2415, 1136, 1649, 5106, 1653, 4474, 4859, 3581}",45,"['Cubans', 'US', 'November 2', 'the 306th day of the year', '307th', 'Gregorian', '59 days', 'the end of the year']","['NORP', 'GPE', 'DATE', 'DATE', 'NORP', 'NORP', 'DATE', 'DATE']"
28,1966,December,8,US and USSR sign treaty to prohibit nuclear weapons in outer space,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treaty_on_the_Non-Proliferation_of_Nuclear_Weapons,"The Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons, commonly known as the Non-Proliferation Treaty or NPT, is an international treaty whose objective is to prevent the spread of nuclear weapons and weapons technology, to promote cooperation in the peaceful uses of nuclear energy, and to further the goal of achieving nuclear disarmament and general and complete disarmament. Between 1965 and 1968, the treaty was negotiated by the Eighteen Nation Committee on Disarmament, a United Nations-sponsored organization based in Geneva, Switzerland.
